Why did His Majesty want to see me here?
‪殿下为何突然找我来这？
Your Majesty.
‪殿下
What…
‪殿…
What could this be about?
‪您为何推我？
I would rather you not tease me, Your Majesty.
‪请别再戏弄我了 殿下
Tease you?
‪戏弄？
I am quite serious.
‪这不是啊
Pardon?
‪什么？
I remember what you once told me.
‪郑注书曾说过
That you would endure everything.
‪你会承担一切
I will do the same.
‪我也要来试试
I am ready to bear the consequences of my feelings.
‪试着来承担我的这份情意
EPISODE 16
‪第 16 集
DIARIES OF THE ROYAL SECRETARIAT MONTHS 7 AND 8
‪（承政院 辛丑年七、八月日记合）
"The late King's body became swollen
‪“先王升遐后过了一天半
after a day and a half since his death."
‪大行王的龙体浮肿
"And his gums blackened."
‪牙龈转为黑色”
After a day and a half?
‪过了一天半吗？
"Great Lord Changcheon used poison from the busohwa plant to murder…"
‪“畅天君利用不消花之毒弑杀…”
His body would have…
‪不消花的话
reacted immediately to busohwa.
‪毒发反应会立即出现啊
Scribe Jung, we should hurry and finish writing the diaries.
‪郑注书 我们尽快把日记整理好吧
Where are you going? We have work to do.
‪你不工作要上哪去？
Allow me to visit the library in the royal infirmary for a moment.
‪我先去一趟内医院书库
Why do you need to go there?
‪你去内医院书库做什么？
Wait…
‪等等…
I guess I will finish them. This is going to take a while.
‪那我来整理 只是会耗时许久
Who goes there?
‪是谁在里面？
Check the back door.
‪去确认门那一侧
-Yes, my lord.
‪-是！
Check if anything is missing.
‪确认一下有没有东西遗失
There were no ledgers on weapon transactions at the office of the guild.
‪商团里找不到武器交易的资料
It seems he did not leave any evidence there.
‪看来是没有留存在那个地方
I should search the base in Yeoyeon.
‪我得直接前往闾延的私兵基地才行了
It must be there seeing how it was not at the office.
‪若在商团找不到 那肯定就放在那里
It would be too dangerous.
‪这样不会太危险吗？
The army base must have tighter security than the office.
‪那里的戒备肯定会比商团还要森严
Do not worry, Your Majesty. I will report back once I return.
‪请不用担心 殿下 我回来再向您禀报
Right. If you need to reach me for an urgent matter,
‪对了 若有什么紧急消息要通知我
send Kang Eun-seo as a messenger.
‪请通过姜溵曙那孩子来传达
I will.
‪我知道了
Please be careful.
‪请务必小心
Busohwa…
‪不消花
"Consumption of busohwa causes swelling in the stomach
‪“摄取不消花后腹部会发胀
and blackens the gums."
‪牙龈转为黑色的症状
"These symptoms appear immediately."
‪会立即出现”
Eunuch Hong, may I ask what brings you here at this hour again?
‪尚膳大人 这个时间 ‪你怎么又到这里来？
Well, it is a great night so I was taking a stroll again.
‪我这次也是因为天气很好就出来散步
-Come with me. -We cannot go with you.
‪-来 随我来吧 ‪-这样不行
Why not? Let me show you a better spot. Come with me.
‪这是什么话？ ‪我给你们看更好的景致 随我来
-We are busy. -Come on. Stop being so stubborn.
‪-我们很忙 ‪-瞧瞧你 真是的
I know a better spot.
‪就说有更好的景致了
After making one mistake,
‪曾犯下一个过失的人
it is easy to make another.
‪也会犯下其他过失
It is why I cannot condone
‪因此我连一次失误
even a single mistake.
‪都不允许
Father.
‪爹
What are you doing here?
‪你在这里做什么？
I would like to ask you the same thing.
‪那爹在这里做什么？
Your Majesty, did the talk go well?
‪殿下 你们谈得还顺利吗？
Let's go back.
‪-回去吧 ‪-是
Your mother must be waiting. Go home now.
‪你娘肯定在等门 我们快回去吧
Did you take care of the Minister of Taxation?
‪户判处理掉了吗？
Yes, my lord.
‪是
The Inspector General's daughter
‪大司宪之女
and your son have been acquainted.
‪和你儿子曾有过几面之缘
What do you think about their union?
‪促成他们的婚事 你觉得如何？
Political alliances are formed through matrimonies.
‪反正政治就是以联姻来结盟的
I suppose it would not be a bad idea if the Inspector General approves of it.
‪若大司宪首肯的话 这也不是件坏事
Right. I hear there was
‪对了 昨夜有人
an intruder at the office of the guild last night.
‪潜入商团之中
Someone broke into the office that handled weapons transactions
‪用来进行武器交易的商团
right when the Minister of Taxation was impeached from his post.
‪在户判遭到弹劾之时发生了那种事
I need you to make a trip to Yeoyeon.
‪看来需要你跑一趟闾延
You are to bring back all the ledgers that could be used
‪那些足以构成 ‪培养私兵证据的相关账簿
to prove the existence of the private army.
‪得全数整理好带回来
Yes, my lord.
‪是 大监
More people in the Ministry of Taxation had been involved with the recent incident
‪户曹中涉入本次 ‪漕运船之案的人数增多
so they are being investigated by the Office of the Inspector General.
‪司宪府正在着手调查
I believe you will have to appoint
‪不久后殿下便要替户曹
a good number of people for the Ministry.
‪广为任用新的人才
I understand.
‪知道了
Your Majesty. Pyongan Province, Hamgil Province,
‪殿下 本次因户曹之事
and Yeonbyeon will not have enough food
‪平安道、咸吉道与延边
due to what the Minister of Taxation has done.
‪各郡县的军粮可能会不够充裕
Scribe Jung.
‪郑注书
Scribe Jung. Please focus.
‪郑注书 请专心一点
What has been on your mind all day?
‪你一整天都在想什么想得那么出神？
I did not get enough sleep last night.
‪我昨夜睡眠不足
Her Majesty the Queen is approaching.
‪中殿娘娘走过来了
I heard that you came back together with the Inspector General.
‪寡人听闻你跟大司宪一道回来了
Yes, Your Majesty.
‪是的 殿下
But what brings you to the palace?
‪不过你怎么会进宫？
Her Highness invited me.
‪小女子受到中殿娘娘的邀请
She had been a close friend of mine before I was married.
‪她是我成亲之前的挚友
The Grand Queen Dowager allowed me to invite her to the palace.
‪大王大妃娘娘也同意我邀她入宫
I see.
‪这样啊
I am deeply indebted to you for everything you have done for me.
‪过去小女子承蒙殿下施予莫大的恩泽
Don't mention it.
‪别这么说
You must have a lot to talk about after not seeing each other for so long.
‪你们许久不见 应该有很多话要说
I should let you go to your quarters.
‪尽快回中宫殿吧
I will tell the Bureau of Special Foods to serve you good tea and refreshments.
‪我会吩咐生果房奉上好茶和餐点
Thank you, Your Majesty.
‪圣恩浩荡 殿下
Let's go.
‪走吧
Then I will head over to Seungjeongwon.
‪那臣回承政院了 殿下
I hear you are in charge of the Diaries of the Royal Secretariat.
‪听说政院日记是由你全权负责
You should get some sleep if you are tired.
‪太累的话就闭目养神一下
I am all right.
‪我没事
Scribe Jung.
‪郑注书
Can I have a moment?
‪借一步说话
Yes, Your Highness?
‪是 娘娘
Could you stop by my quarters if you have some time to spare?
‪你能抽空到中宫殿一趟吗？
Pardon?
‪什么？
Your Highness.
‪娘娘
There are some things I want to ask you about life at the palace.
‪本宫有些关于宫里的事想请教你
And I happen to run into you here.
‪碰巧就在这里遇到你
It will only take a moment.
‪只要占用你一点时间就好
I'm not sure if I will meet the expectations.
‪小女子没有自信能胜任世子嫔
Do you have feelings for someone else?
‪请问你的心里是否另有意中人了？
Please forgive me.
‪小女子惶恐
Should I make a trip to the Queen's quarters?
‪要小的去中宫殿一趟吗？
I can go and observe.
‪去观察一下情况
Observe?
‪观察什么情况？
The night when the lanterns were lit,
‪那天灯火通明时
you and Scribe Jung shared a kiss.
‪你们两位双唇贴合
I do not know what you are talking about.
‪我不晓得你在胡说些什么
Goodness.
‪真是的
Do not worry.
‪您不必太担心
I will not tell Court Lady Kim about this.
‪小的会向金尚宫娘娘保密
I will head over there now.
‪那小的去去就回
That is not…
‪不是…
I heard that you have crossed paths before.
‪听说你们俩之前就有过几面之缘
And here you are, running into each other at the palace again.
‪现在你们又这样偶然重逢
Some bonds are indeed extraordinary
‪缘分真的很不可思议呢
just like the bond between His Majesty and me.
‪就像本宫与殿下的相遇一般
Yes, indeed.
‪是的 您说得没错
The bond is indeed strange. No.
‪缘分还真奇怪…不
It is extraordinary.
‪是不可思议
His Majesty has sent some refreshments.
‪中殿娘娘 殿下下赐茶点
Lend me a hand.
‪帮我一下
How kind of him to send us refreshments.
‪殿下居然如此用心
Please tell him I am very grateful.
‪请转告殿下本宫很感激
Yes, Your Highness.
‪是 娘娘
By the way,
‪不过
you are at the best age to marry.
‪郑注书已届适婚年纪
Why are you still alone?
‪为何还没娶回美娇娘呢？
Pardon?
‪什么？
Well, I…
‪那我还没…
Are you all right?
‪你还好吗？
Thank you.
‪谢谢你
Your Highness, that question may have been too personal.
‪娘娘 您为何问这么私人的问题？
Where are my manners?
‪瞧瞧我真是口无遮拦
I am so sorry.
‪真的很抱歉
My question was indeed too personal.
‪我的问题太私人了对吧？
It is all right, Your Highness.
‪您别这么说 娘娘
Will that be all?
‪你怎么站在那里呢？
Yes, Your Highness.
‪是 娘娘
I will take my leave now.
‪那小的就先告退了
Please thank His Majesty for me.
‪请务必替我向殿下转达感谢之情
Yes, Your Highness.
‪是 娘娘
Your Majesty.
‪殿下
So tell me. Are they enjoying each other's company?
‪好 他们相谈甚欢吗？
Yes. But you do not have to worry about anything.
‪是 您不必过于操心
I was not worried.
‪我才没有操心
You may leave.
‪你出去吧
Yes, Your Majesty.
‪是
I can see that His Majesty cherishes you.
‪殿下对娘娘真的十分深情体贴
He makes sure to take care of you like this.
‪居然如此用心
I suppose.
‪就是说啊
I hope you will also meet someone nice soon.
‪我也希望你能尽快找到如意郎君
And you too, Scribe Jung.
‪郑注书也是
Right.
‪好的
Your Highness.
‪娘娘
There is something I have been wanting to give you.
‪有样东西我一直想在你入宫时拿给你
Wait here for a moment.
‪等我一下喔
I did not know you would be here.
‪我不晓得你在宫中任职
When did you return from Onyang?
‪你是何时从温阳回来的？
Well…
‪那个…
I came back a while ago.
‪有段时日了
Actually, a lot has happened since I returned.
‪坦白说 这段时间发生了很多事
Her Highness has misunderstood our history
‪中殿娘娘似乎误会了我们之间的缘分
and left us in private on purpose.
‪才会特地回避让我们独处
You seemed busy.
‪你似乎很忙的样子
I will talk to Her Highness for you, so you can take your leave.
‪我会好好跟娘娘解释 你先走吧
Then could you speak to her on my behalf?
‪那可以麻烦你代为跟她解释吗？
I have some people to meet with outside the palace.
‪其实我在宫外跟人有约了
Right. You know them too.
‪对了 你应该认识他们
Jil-geum and Yeong-ji, my friends from Samgaebang.
‪是质昑和英持 三开房的孩子们
I hope they are all well.
‪他们都过得很好吧？
Of course.
‪那当然
They would still be standing even if the world came to an end.
‪他们就算世界毁灭了也能活下去
It was a pleasure to see you again.
‪再次相逢真的很开心
Wait.
‪我…
I was worried that…
‪一直很担心上次最后见到少爷时
I had made you feel uncomfortable because I only thought about my feelings
‪是不是太急于表达自己的情感
the last time I saw you.
‪而让你感到不舒服
No. You do not need to feel that way.
‪不 没有那回事
You seem drawn compared to the last time I saw you.
‪你似乎变得比初次见到时还消瘦
I heard your family had a tough time.
‪听说你家遭逢了变故
I am glad you are back.
‪我很高兴你回来了
Coming back to a place where you had been hurt
‪要做出回到饱受煎熬之处
must not have been an easy decision.
‪这种决定可不简单
Leave your past behind you and look after yourself.
‪把往事暂时抛诸脑后 ‪并多加照顾自己
And do not blame yourself either.
‪请不要自责
Goodbye.
‪在下告辞
Where is Scribe Jung?
‪郑注书呢？
Please forgive me. I told him it was okay to take his leave.
‪小女子惶恐 我叫他先走了
Really?
‪真的吗？
Did I make you two feel uncomfortable?
‪是本宫让你们感到不自在吗？
No, Your Highness.
‪没这回事 娘娘
Why are you here?
‪你为何在这里？
The reception at the Queen's quarters must still be ongoing.
‪中宫殿的茶点聚会应该还没有结束啊
There is something I must take care of outside the palace.
‪我有事得出宫一趟
I see.
‪这样啊
So tell me. Did you enjoy the reception?
‪好 那个茶点聚会还尽兴吗？
Yes, I enjoyed it. Thank you for the refreshments.
‪是的 很感谢您 ‪送过去的美味茶点 殿下
They were not for you.
‪那不是要给你
They were for the Queen.
‪而是送给中殿吃的
I see.
‪是这样吗？
What is the matter?
‪不过您为何板着一张脸？
What do you mean?
‪你指什么？
Did I do something wrong?
‪是我做错了什么吗？
What is that look on your face?
‪你为何那副表情？
Well…
‪那个…
It is nothing.
‪没什么
Why are you smiling like that?
‪你干吗老是那样笑？
Well, I believe
‪没什么啦
you might be jealous right now.
‪殿下似乎在吃醋
It makes me happy.
‪让我心情很好
What?
‪什么？
Why would I be jealous?
‪谁吃醋了？
Do not get the wrong idea.
‪你不要自作多情了
Please do not worry. I will be back soon, Your Majesty.
‪请不用担心 我马上就会回来 殿下
Commander Jung wishes to enter.
‪内禁卫长求见
Let him in.
‪让他进来
Allow me to take a leave for a few days to inspect security
‪为了察看齐贤大君于江华住所的戒备
at Prince Jehyeon's dwelling in Ganghwa.
‪臣得离开几天
All of a sudden?
‪为何如此突然？
Did something happen to Gyeom?
‪谦发生了什么事吗？
It is my seasonal inspection.
‪这只是每季的例行巡查
I see. You have my approval.
‪知道了 你去吧
-Jil-geum. -Hey.
‪-质昑 ‪-嗯
What took you so long?
‪大哥 你为什么姗姗来迟？
I have a lot of clients at the clinic.
‪最近我们药房门庭若市
So I cannot be gone for too long.
‪我不能出来太久
Sorry about that.
‪对不起啦
Fine. So what is this about?
‪好吧 是什么事？
I need to ask you for a favor.
‪没什么 只是你得帮我一个忙
-A favor? -I need you to go to the herb markets…
‪-帮忙？ ‪-你去药草市场的时候
and find out about this plant.
‪帮我打听一下这种草
I do not think it is a common herb in Joseon.
‪这似乎不易在朝鲜取得
See if you can find any vendors who are knowledgeable about herbs
‪你去打听是否有药草商 ‪对明国或西域的药草有所研究
Is this a poisonous herb?
‪莫非是毒草？
Do this for me. Bye.
‪拜托你 我先走了
-Be careful. -Yes, my lord.
‪-小心点 ‪-是
I deserve to die!
‪小的罪该万死！
My fingers got slippery when I was trying to put it in.
‪小的要放胎函时手指一滑
So it is broken now.
‪就打破了
Whom does it belong to?
‪那是谁的胎函？
Well…
‪那个是…
this placenta chest belongs to His Majesty.
‪主上殿下的胎函
Twins?
‪双胞胎？
It is in my understanding that umbilical cords
‪以双胞胎出生的孩子中
can take on this shape
‪偶尔会出现在母亲腹中 ‪脐带就交缠的情况
when the umbilical cords of twins get tangled inside the womb.
‪听说就是呈现这个样子
Do not speak to anyone about what you saw today.
‪你今天看到的一切不准告诉任何人
Yes, my lord!
‪是
They are the ones who banished Prince Jehyeon all the way to Ganghwa.
‪他们自己把齐贤大君流放到那里
Now, they are going to check on him every season? How ridiculous.
‪现在却说要每季去察看 真是可笑
We must hold off on our plan in Yeoyeon.
‪看来闾延之事得先缓缓
Send a letter to Eun-seo.
‪捎信给溵曙
Eun-seo?
‪溵曙？
I am talking about Kim Ga-on.
‪就是金佳稳那孩子
I am not used to his real name. I will do so, Your Majesty.
‪小的还没适应那个本名
After all, Prince Jaeun is a member of the royal family.
‪者隐君毕竟是宗亲的身份
It seems he has stopped coming to your quarters
‪他在得知殿下的秘密后
after finding out the truth about you.
‪似乎就不再到大殿来了
I reckon that he is doing so out of consideration for you
‪他也许是担心您感到不自在
in case you feel uncomfortable.
‪出于体贴才会这么做吧
Hyun.
‪王兄
Your Majesty.
‪殿下
Have you been busy these days?
‪你近来很忙吗？
You have not come to see me lately.
‪我完全都没见到你
What is it? Is something wrong?
‪怎么了？发生了什么事吗？
Whenever I tell you this,
‪当我这么告诉你的时候
you always worry first and ask me
‪你总是会先忧心忡忡地问我
if something has happened.
‪是否发生了什么事
Sitting here with you
‪跟你一同坐在这里
reminds me of a day from a long time ago.
‪让我想起许久前一起度过的那一天
You were worried that I would be scared
‪你担心我待在陌生的地方会害怕
to be in a new place, so you read books for me until deep into the night.
‪所以念书给我听直至夜深
You always enjoyed books.
‪殿下本来就很喜欢书
And you still do.
‪无论是以前还是现在
The candy you gave me then
‪那时王兄让我
was the first I had ever tasted.
‪第一次尝到糖的味道
It was the first time I tasted something that sweet.
‪那是我出生以来初次尝到的甜蜜滋味
When I had it in my mouth,
‪糖在我嘴里融化时
I was able to forget all the fear I had about the palace.
‪美好得足以让我将入宫的恐惧
I was happy.
‪全都抛诸脑后
I will bring you some more.
‪要再替您拿一点过来吗？
As much as you need.
‪只要您开口 要多少有多少
Ever since I was young,
‪自小对我来说
I felt the most comfortable around you…
‪王兄就是相处起来最自在
and you were the person I relied on the most.
‪让我最为依赖的人
-Your Majesty. -So could you continue…
‪-殿下 ‪-所以往后也请你继续
to treat me the way you used to?
‪这样自在地面对我 好吗？
When I see you distancing yourself from me,
‪王兄这样保持距离
I do not know…
‪也让我
how to behave around you either.
‪不晓得该如何面对你
If I ask you…
‪若日后
to remain as my good cousin and closest friend…
‪我也请你以好王兄 ‪及最亲近友人的身份
by my side,
‪留在我身边的话
would I be asking for too much?
‪会显得我太贪心吗？
You could never ask too much of me. Of course, I will do so.
‪怎么会贪心呢？我当然会那么做
You will forever be my king, Your Majesty.
‪殿下是我永远的君主啊
What is this?
‪这是什么东西？
It is a present for you.
‪这是送给邸下的礼物
Why are you giving me this?
‪你怎么会送我这种东西？
When you find a lady you love and get engaged,
‪等你以后有了情人就送给对方吧
Hello, Uncle.
‪你来了啊 叔父
His Majesty will remove you from your position
‪殿下很快就会撤掉叔父的职牒
and banish you to Gyeongsang Province.
‪将你放逐至庆尚道
What?
‪你说什么？
What…
‪怎么…
I cannot believe this nonsense.
‪怎么会有这么荒诞无稽的事？
Why? What have I done wrong?
‪为什么？我做错什么了？
Why?
‪为什么？
Tell him to just kill me.
‪叫他干脆杀掉我算了
No. I shall go over there and kill everyone.
‪不 我直接去把那里的人全数歼灭
Then I shall end my life there!
‪然后在原地自我了断
I will help you get your revenge.
‪叔父的怨愤由我来替你纾解
Put your life in my hands.
‪把你的性命交付给我吧
I know something very useful.
‪我手上有张绝佳的牌
Hey.
‪喂
Useful enough to bring down the Crown Prince.
‪那是张足以击溃世子的牌
Something is off about Jung Seok-jo.
‪我总觉得郑析助的行动很可疑
Go and tell Officer Yoon
‪转告副护军
to postpone his trip to Yeoyeon for the time being.
‪前往闾延一事暂先推迟
Officer Yoon left last night in a haste
‪副护军至北方边界察看
to check the border in the northern region.
‪他昨晚就急忙动身前往了
-Last night? -Yes.
‪-昨晚吗？ ‪-是的
-What is it? -A suspicious man has been spotted.
‪-什么事？ ‪-出现了可疑之人
What?
‪什么？
TRANSACTION ON DAY 23 AT NAKDONG, GYEONGSANG PROVINCE
‪（23日 庆尚道梁山郡 洛东）
It seems I've arrived earlier than you expected.
‪看来我比你预期中还早抵达
I warned you before
‪我上次就说过了
that I would not turn a blind eye next time.
‪下次碰到就不会轻易放过你
Do you still believe
‪那天你对我说的那番话
what you told me before?
‪你到现在还是那么想吗？
Do you still think that this is the only path you can take?
‪你能走的就只有那条路吗？
Have you ever regretted your decision?
‪你曾后悔做了那个选择吗？
Your decision to stand by Lord Sangheon.
‪与尚宪君并肩同行的选择
This was the only path I was given.
‪我仅是因为只能走这条路
So I merely walked my path.
‪才走来这里的
-Are you all right? -How…
‪-你还好吗？ ‪-你…
Intruders!
‪你们是谁？
You must leave.
‪请先避开吧
Come with me. Hurry!
‪快随我来 快啊！
Chase them! Go!
‪追上去！快啊！
Get them!
‪抓住他们！
-Get them!
‪-抓住他们！
Hurry.
‪动作快
Get them!
‪追上去！
Give me the ledger.
‪把账簿交出来
And I will spare your life.
‪那我就饶你一命
Is that your last favor as a friend?
‪这是身为朋友最后的体贴吗？
Take it.
‪拜托你了
No!
‪不可以！
Go!
‪你快走！
Stay alive.
‪活下去
Stop!
‪快住手！
Seok-jo…
‪析助
The sky is beautiful.
‪天空真美
Here is what I think.
‪我仔细一想
I bet you spent the whole night training alone.
‪你昨夜肯定又自己练了一整晚
I am certain of it.
‪你绝对又练了一整夜
I think you need some more training.
‪你应该要多练一些才是
Come on.
‪真是可恶
You…
‪真受不了你
Goodness.
‪唉唷
Seok-jo. Look at the sky.
‪析助 你看天空
How beautiful.
‪真的好美
Goodness.
‪天啊
Hyeong-seol.
‪炯设
No.
‪不可以
I believe he was unable to take the ledger.
‪他应该没办法带走账簿
And Officer Yoon…
‪副护军…
died on the spot.
‪当场就断气了
After paying a price like that,
‪既然付出了那样的代价
I am sure
‪殿下现在
His Majesty will learn a lesson from all of this.
‪应该有所醒悟了吧
-Ji-un, over here! -Hey, Jil-geum.
‪-大哥 这里 ‪-质昑
Did you find what I asked for?
‪我拜托你的找到了吗？
You said the corpse got swollen and changed color after a day and a half.
‪你说尸体过了一天半后 ‪才开始浮肿、变色对吧？
I think this might be it.
‪我想应该是这个
SONANGCHO
‪（苏朗草）
A RARE, POISONOUS PLANT THAT FLOWERS EVERY TWO TO THREE YEARS
‪（花由二三年即一开 稀贵植物也）
Your Majesty.
‪殿下
Scribe Jung. Have you not gone home yet?
‪郑注书 你还没离宫吗？
-I need to speak with you, Your Majesty. -What?
‪-臣有事要向您禀报 殿下 ‪-什么？
All right. Come with me.
‪好 随我来吧
BONCHOGANGMOK
‪（《本草纲目》）
What is this?
‪这是什么？
The Diaries of the Royal Secretariat state
‪根据承政院日记中的记录
that the poisonous herb that killed the late King was busohwa.
‪导致先王殿下身亡的毒草是不消花
Right. I was informed of this as well.
‪对 我听到的也是那样
And I also read the Diaries.
‪我也确认过政院日记了
It was all fabricated.
‪那全是捏造的
When one gets poisoned with busohwa,
‪死于不消花的情况是
the postmortem signs are supposed to show up immediately.
‪尸体会于死后立即出现毒物反应
But it took
‪但先王殿下
a day and a half for these signs to become visible on the late King's body.
‪是经过了一天半后才出现毒物反应
What are you…
‪那是什么意思？
SONANGCHO
‪（苏朗草）
It was sonangcho.
‪是苏朗草
It is much more poisonous than busohwa.
‪此种毒草的毒性比不消花更强
And they bring out similar postmortem signs.
‪死后呈现的反应虽然相似
But it is incredibly difficult to find this herb.
‪但却十分难以取得
-Then… -If we find the distribution chain,
‪-那么… ‪-只要找出此种毒草流通的地方
we will be able to find out the truth behind the late King's death.
‪就能揭开先王殿下枉死的真相了
SONANGCHO
‪（苏朗草）
Your Majesty.
‪殿下
What is it?
‪有什么事？
News has come from Yeoyeon.
‪闾延那边捎来消息了
News?
‪消息？
Where is…
‪副护军…
Officer Yoon?
‪在哪里？
He passed away.
‪他过世了
Officer Yoon told me to make sure this was delivered to you.
‪副护军吩咐我一定要转交给殿下
Could you escort those two back to the palace?
‪你送他们俩回到王宫
I want to stay here for a bit longer.
‪我还想在这里待一会
Yes, Your Majesty.
‪是 殿下
Thank you.
‪谢谢你
For coming back alive.
‪活着回来
I feel as if I am surrounded by fog.
‪我总觉得自己在雾中徘徊
When I run somewhere, thinking it is my final destination,
‪当我认定某个地方是目的地向前跑时
I realize that the destination
‪那个目的地在转眼间
is actually still far away.
‪就变得十分遥远
And when I run with all my might,
‪又再次奋力向前跑时
it gets farther away.
‪它就离得更远
I have been wandering around to no end.
‪在无止境的徘徊后
And now,
‪现在
I feel like I have forgotten
‪我却有种连要走的路在哪里
where I need to go.
‪都迷失的感觉
Will I…
‪我能重新
be able to find my way again?
‪找到我的路吗？
Will the fog
‪那片雾
ever go away?
‪会散去吗？
Once the rain stops, the sun will shine.
‪雨停了 阳光就会照耀
Once the fog lifts,
‪雾散了
the view will become clear.
‪远处的风景就会变得鲜明
If you have a destination, you will reach it someday.
‪若是您有立定的目的地 ‪总有一天会到达的
No matter how long it takes.
‪不管要花费多少时间
What brings you to the Capital? I was not informed of your visit.
‪你怎么没通知一声就突然回到都城？
The news of Officer Yoon's death has reached my ears.
‪我听说了副护军过世的消息
I know that His Majesty respected him.
‪殿下相当尊敬他
He must be grieving.
‪心里肯定很难过
Yes.
‪是的
Is that why you are here?
‪你是因为那个才回来的吗？
How is the relocation of the placenta chamber going?
‪迁移胎室一事怎么样了？
Is it going well?
‪进行得还顺利吗？
The task was more interesting than I expected.
‪那比我想象的还有趣呢
I do not know how to thank
‪真不晓得该如何感谢
Lord Sangheon for giving me this task.
‪推派我去的尚宪君
I am glad to hear that.
‪真是太好了
I was worried that life in the countryside would be difficult.
‪我还很担心乡村的生活 ‪会让你感到很辛苦
Do not worry.
‪你不用担心
It seems I have a very good chance of coming back earlier than planned.
‪看来我能比计划中还早回到都城
What a beautiful sound.
‪这声音好美
It sounds like waves.
‪听起来就像海浪声
You asked me to come to the seaside with you.
‪你曾邀我一起去海边
I am sorry.
‪很抱歉
It does not have to be the seaside.
‪不一定非得要去海边
I just wanted
‪我只是
to stay by your side.
‪想留在殿下身边罢了
You told me to trust you rather than die a meaningless death.
‪你说与其死得一文不值 ‪倒不如相信你一回
But what is this if not a meaningless death?
‪但这不是死得一文不值的话 ‪是什么？
You were supposed to take the throne and bring me back
‪你说在齐贤大君的势力没落后
after ousting Prince Jehyeon and his people.
‪你会登上王位 并带我回去
I have sent thousands of letters to you!
‪我光是捎给你的书信就有千百封了！
This is quite the greeting.
‪你的问候还真热烈
Please calm down, Uncle.
‪冷静一点 叔父
Fine. Why did you want to see me now? What is it?
‪好 你找我过来是有何居心？
Do you need me now that you got kicked out of the Capital?
‪你现在被逐出都城就开始需要我啦？
What is it? Do you want me to accompany you to the afterlife?
‪怎么？要我陪你一起下黄泉吗？
I do not think that will be necessary.
‪应该没有那个必要
I asked you to come here so that I could bring you back from the afterlife.
‪我是要让叔父脱离那个地方
If there are two umbilical cords…
‪两条脐带的话
Does it mean they were twins?
‪是双胞胎的意思吗？
If you are trying to fool me again…
‪你敢再耍我一次…
Damn it.
‪该死
Fine. So go on. Why is the fact that they were twins important?
‪好 所以双胞胎又怎么样了？
In the year His Majesty was born,
‪殿下出生的那一年
you must remember that many from the delivery chamber were killed.
‪产室厅曾变成一片血海 ‪这件事你知道吗？
So you managed to find out.
‪你居然能耳闻到这些
No one speaks of it as it is a secret.
‪因为那是个秘密 都无人敢提起
What if they were all killed to cover up a certain truth?
‪那如果赶尽杀绝 ‪是为了要掩盖某个秘密
What do you think?
‪你觉得会是如何？
For example,
‪例如
His Majesty becoming a different person at a certain point.
‪殿下从某一刻起换成了另一个人
A different person?
‪换人？
When His Majesty was the Prince,
‪殿下在世孙时期时
Hyun told me something.
‪显曾说过这种话
He said it felt as if the Prince had become someone else.
‪世孙感觉变了一个人
We both sensed it too, did we not?
‪我们不是也有感受到吗？
I understand he wanted to keep a distance from us,
‪就算要跟宗亲保持距离
but he was oddly fastidious about not participating in activities
‪但只要是男人间的聚会 ‪他每次都会缺席
where there were only men.
‪那非比寻常的洁癖
I was right?
‪我说得对吧？
Yes, indeed! I told you!
‪天杀的 对嘛 我就说了啊！
What I told you was true!
‪我脑中的那个想法是对的 该死！
I was right!
‪被我说对了！
Now, I believe
‪现在我也觉得
that you may have been right
‪或许叔父所提出的论点
about this.
‪是对的
So I just need to check whether or not he is a woman?
‪所以只要确定殿下 ‪是不是女儿身就好 对吧？
You have swelling around your eyes.
‪您的眼睛很肿该如何是好？
There is nothing I can do.
‪那也别无他法啊
I cannot be gone for long.
‪我不能离宫太久
-What is this? -You have to get away from here.
‪-你们是什么人？ ‪-您得尽快躲避
Uncle, how…
‪叔父怎么会…
Your Majesty.
‪殿下
Father.
‪爹
Did you check if he was indeed a woman?
‪你确认过殿下是否为女儿身了吗？
He is a woman. I'm certain of it.
‪我确定她是女的
A woman? You must have gone mad!
‪女的？你疯了吧？
His Majesty sees Scribe Jung in private?
‪殿下会私下跟郑注书见面？
Is it possible His Majesty prefers men to women?
‪比起女子 殿下会不会更喜欢男人？
Is that why he is avoiding sleeping with the Queen?
‪所以才会不断回避 ‪跟中殿娘娘合房吧？
You should stop seeing Scribe Jung for the time being.
‪您暂时得避免跟郑注书见面了 殿下
I will not ask you for the truth.
‪臣妾不会问您真相是什么
Just allow me to produce an heir.
‪请让我生个继承人就好
I do not want to lose you, Your Majesty.
‪我不想失去殿下
I am getting married.
‪我会成亲的
Subtitle translation by: Won-hyang Son
‪字幕翻译：钟见悦